Sameh Mabrouk

<u>mabrouksameh@gmail.com</u> | https://samehmabrouk.tech
<u>LinkedIn</u> | GitHub | Stack Overflow | Medium

Summary

Senior software engineer, specializing in developing iOS apps, but curious about everything.

I love solving hard problems, learning new domains, and creating big systems that are manageable and amenable to change. In order to help my whole team succeed, I find and remove obstacles, answer a lot of smart questions, and try to ask even more dumb questions.

Experience

iOS Platform Lead, Temper

December 2019 - PRESENT, Amsterdam - Netherlands

- Leads Temper iOS App development
- Works closely with product owners and design teams to convert ideas, designs, and requirements into production builds using agile processes
- Leads architecture discussions and code reviews to constantly find the best solutions
- Influences and mentor peers through 1:1s and pair programming sessions
- Proactively maintains a relationship with individual members of the iOS chapter, possibly through 1:1s

iOS Team Lead, VanMoof

December 2018 - November 2019, Amsterdam - Netherlands

- Built <u>VanMoof</u> iOS App
- Built iOS team at VanMoof and support recruiting of talents
- Kick-started team's processes and guidelines for Scrum, TDD, unit test, XCUITest, Swift, & code review
- Automated continuous integration/delivery with Jenkins, fastlane, CocoaPods
- Gave feedback and collaborating with our UX designer to improve how our riders use our app

Senior iOS Engineer, Tigets

January 2018 - November 2018, Amsterdam - Netherlands

- Worked on <u>Tigets</u> iOS App
- Worked closely with the Product owner, continuously implementing new features according to the client's needs.
- Refined existing code-base by refactoring using common object oriented programming design patterns.
- Implemented TDD, Automated testing, and constant refactoring

Senior iOS Engineer, **Philips**

October 2016 - December 2017, Amsterdam - Netherlands

- Worked as Contractor (from Mobiguity) for Philips healthcare mobile apps like <u>SleepMapper</u>
- Worked closely with the Project Manager, continuously implementing new features according to the client's needs.
- Refining existing code-base by refactoring using common object oriented programming design patterns.
- Implemented TDD, Automated testing, and constant refactoring.

Senior iOS Engineer, Mobiquity

October 2016 - December 2017, Amsterdam - Netherlands

- Developed iOS Apps like <u>Vomar</u> using Swift and Objective C.
- Kick-started team's processes and guidelines for Scrum, TDD, unit test, Swift, & code review
- Modeling UML architectures employing design patterns & SOLID principles.
- Automated continuous integration/delivery with Jenkins, fastlane, CocoaPods.

Freelance Senior iOS Engineer, Digiflare

March 2016 - October 2016, Toronto - Canada

- Worked closely with the Project Manager, continuously implementing new features according to the client's needs.
- Daily/weekly status reports and Agile planning sessions.
- Refined existing code-base by refactoring using common object-oriented programming design patterns.
- Implemented TDD, Automated testing, and constant refactoring.
- Dependency injection.
- Worked on products like <u>TSN Go</u> and Eclipse Apple TV App.

Senior iOS Engineer, Mentor Graphics

May 2014 - September 2016, Cairo - Egypt

- Developed, maintained, and enhanced iOS applications.
- Developed web services/RESTful API.
- Shipped several releases of <u>EZMobilePrint</u>.
- Developed and deployed web applications with J2EE(WildFly), Javascript(JQuery)/HTML/CSS.

Mobile Application developer, Alzwad

Jun 2011 - April 2014, Cairo - Egypt

- Maintained and enhanced iOS and Android applications
- Translated business requirements and mock-ups into fully functioning features
- Partnered with designers to help define and implement User Interfaces
- Provided estimates on development cycles
- Worked with other teams on server-side integration

Skills Technical Skills:

Expert in:

- iOS Development
- Objective-C
- Swift
- UIKit, Cocoa Touch, Quartz(Core Graphics), Core Animation, Core Data, Grand Central Dispatch, Xcode.
- TDD, unit testing with XCTest, automated acceptance testing with <u>Calabash</u>, <u>Appium</u>, UI Automation, XCode UI Test)
- BDD with <u>Kiwi</u>
- Dependency injection and OOP design patterns.
- Architecture Design patterns (MVC, MVP, MVVM, VIPER)
- Continuous integration with <u>Jenkins</u> and <u>Travis</u>
- Continuous Delivery with <u>Fastlane</u>
- Dependency management with <u>CocoaPods</u> and <u>Carthage</u>
- Agile Methodologies/Scrum/Extreme programming

Proficient in:

- Swift UI
- Reactive programming(RxSwift)
- Java
- Android
- Mac OS X development
- Source control with Git, Subversion and CVS
- GraphQL(Apollo)

Familiar with:

- Web application development using J2EE (Hibernate, Struts, Servlet, JSP, JSTL, EJB, JPA)
- C, C++, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, XML, Web Services, AJAX
- Database design
- Documenting and designing applications with UML
- SQL, Oracle PL/SQL, MySQL, Python, Haskell, J2ME

Personnel Skills:

- Proactive, entrepreneurial thinking and hardworking
- A problem-solver, using analytical and logical abilities in fault finding
- Self-taught and rapid learning

Education

B.Sc., Computer and Information Systems (Computer science)

2007 - 2011, Cairo - Egypt

Diploma of Software Engineering in Information Technology Institute (ITI) – Java department (Mobile Application Developer Track).

2011 - 2012, Cairo - Egypt

Honor & Awards

- Won a Startupbootcamp Berlin 2014 competition with Beliaa product we were one of the 11 teams that were able to pitch to a room full of VC, angels and investors at investor demo day.
- Developed iOS application (Ezzay) and it was one of the shortlisted Mobile Applications in Yalla N'Saytar Competition from Etisalat Egypt.

Certificates

Oracle certified professional java SE 6 programmer

Projects

SleepMapper

SleepMapper is the companion app to the Philips SmartSleep headband. Download the SleepMapper app to awaken to a better day tomorrow. Get support for the healthy sleep you deserve.

Vomar

Vomar Voordeelmarkt is a successful regional supermarket chain with 62 benefit markets in New York, the Bulb, Flevoland and Utrecht. Vomar Voordeelmarkt growing rapidly, partly due to an excellent quality range at very competitive prices. I worked on a feature that enables Admins to add recipes to the website with a team of product owners, scrum master and 3 developers.

TSN Go

The latest game-changing app update from Canada's Sports Leader, TSN GO gives television subscribers the ability to watch TSN1, TSN2, TSN3, TSN4 and TSN5 live on multiple platforms, anytime, anywhere. I developed and shipped the current version of the app (2.17.0).

Eclipse Apple TV

A proof of concept Apple TV application written in swift. My first tvOS app at Digiflare. I worked on 3 Agile sprints to develop and ship many features of this app with a team of 4 developers.

Snake Byte

The classic snake game on Apple Watch. My first Apple Watch app. It's one of the first games for Apple Watch. I released this game on App Store 4 months ago and currently, it has +3000 downloads from different countries like UK, USA, Germany and Australia.

Tweet Speak

iOS app that reads your Twitter feeds out loud. It's a creative and handy app for everyone who likes to read tweets while driving, running, or biking. This is a side project i developed and released in 2014 and it has thousands of downloads.

Hope

Social Aggregated Mobile Platform for Blood Donation, combine different blood donation requests from different Social Networks channels in one place. I created the UI & UX, designed the RESTful API, and developed the complete app.

Zambaleeta

Zambaleeta application is one of the best bilingual (Arabic, English) entertainment and comprehensive application you can ever have. It provides you with the latest News, a huge amount of original music and Videos. One of my first iOS apps at Alzwad, I developed the complete app and participated in a RESTful API design.

ViperCode

Development of open source OS X app for generating VIPER module's skeleton to be used in Objective-C and Swift projects.

Panorama

An open source Objective-C implementation of the photo tilt gesture/UX inspired by Facebook's Paper app.

Panoramic

Open-source Swift implementation of the photo tilt gesture/UX inspired by Facebook's Paper

Beliaa

Road assistance service app. A one-stop instant communication platform between car owners, road rescue centers. I created the UI & UX, designed the RESTful API, and developed the complete app.

Other apps and open source projects I have developed: <u>swift-algorithms</u>, <u>SwiftPad</u>, <u>EZMobilePrint</u>, <u>Foody</u>, <u>Renault</u>, <u>Glassy</u>, <u>Rubber</u>, <u>Summflower</u>, <u>ThatCopy</u>